{"test_questions": [[{"question": "The velocity factor of a transmission line depends on", "opta": "temperature", "optb": "skin effect", "optc": "relative permittivity of dielectric", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "\u2208r of a dielectric changes with humidity."}, {"question": "A loss less line of characteristic impedance Z0 is terminated in pure reactance of -jZ0 value. VSWR is", "opta": "10", "optb": "2", "optc": "1", "optd": "infinity", "ans": "D", "explanation": "A pure reactance does not absorb any power.\nTherefore VSWR is infinite because |rv| = 1."}, {"question": "In a klystron amplifier the input cavity is called", "opta": "buncher", "optb": "catcher", "optc": "Pierce gun", "optd": "collector", "ans": "A", "explanation": "A Klystron is a vacuum tube used for generation/amplification of microwaves. \nAn electron beam is produced by oxide coated indirectly heated cathode and is focussed and accelerated by focussing electrode. \nThis beam is transmitted through a glass tube. The input cavity where the beam enters the glass tube is called buncher. \nAs electrons move ahead they see an accelerating field for half cycle and retarding field for the other half cycle. \nTherefore, some electrons are accelerated and some are retarded. This process is called velocity modulation. \nThe velocity modulation causes bunching of electrons. This bunching effect converts velocity modulation into density modulation of beam. \nThe input is fed at buncher cavity and output is taken at catcher cavity. \nIn a two cavity klystron only buncher and catcher cavity are used. In multi cavity klystron one or more intermediate cavities are also used. \nThe features of a multicavity klystron are :\n1. Frequency range - 0.25 GHz to 100 GHz\n2. Power output - 10 kW to several hundred kW\n3. Power gain - 60 dB (nominal value)\n4. Efficiency - about 40%.\nA multicavity klystron is used in UHF TV transmitters, Radar transmitter and satellite communication."}, {"question": "In a circular waveguide the dominant mode is", "opta": "TE01", "optb": "TE11", "optc": "TE20", "optd": "TE21", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Some applications require dual polarization capability. Circular waveguide has this capability. \nThese analysis uses cylindrical coordinates. \nIn circular waveguide TE11 mode has the lowest cut off frequency and is the dominant mode. \nIf D is diameter of waveguide\n\u03bbc = 1.706 D for TE11 mode\n\u03bbc = 1.029 D for TE21 mode\n\u03bbc = 0.82 D for TE01 mode\n\u03bbc = 1.306 D for TM01 mode."}, {"question": "The reflection coefficient on a line is 0.2 \u222045\u00b0. The SWR is", "opta": "0.8", "optb": "1.1", "optc": "1.2", "optd": "1.5", "ans": "D", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Microwave resonators are used in", "opta": "microwave oscillators", "optb": "microwave narrow band amplifier", "optc": "microwave frequency metres", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "They are used in all the devices."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  TWT uses a focussing mechanism to prevent the electron beam from spreading.Reason (R): In a TWT the electron beam has to travel a much longer distance than in klystron.", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct but R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong but R is correct", "ans": "A", "explanation": "In a klystron the resonant structure limits the bandwidth. \nA TWT is a broadband device. Its main components are electron gun (to produce the electron beam) and a structure supporting the slow electromagnetic wave. \nThe velocity of wave propagation along the helix structure is less than velocity of light. \nThe beam and wave travel along the structure at the same speed. \nThus interaction occurs between beam and wave and the beam delivers energy to the RF wave. \nTherefore the signal gets strengthened and amplified output is delivered at the other end of tube. \nThe main features of TWT are :\n1. Frequency range - 0.5 GHz to 90 GHz\n2. Power output - 5 mW at low frequencies(less than 20 GHz) 250 kW (continuous wave) at 3 GHz 10 MW (pulsed) at 3 GHz\n3. Efficiency - about 5 to 20%\n4. Noise - about 5 dB for low power TWT 25 dB for high power TWT \nTWT is used as RF amplifier in broadband microwave receivers, repeater amplifier in broad band communication systems, communication satellites etc."}, {"question": "In a TWT the amplitude of resultant wave travelling down the helix", "opta": "increases exponentially", "optb": "increases linearly", "optc": "decreases exponentially", "optd": "is almost constant", "ans": "A", "explanation": "In a klystron the resonant structure limits the bandwidth. \nA TWT is a broadband device. Its main components are electron gun (to produce the electron beam) and a structure supporting the slow electromagnetic wave. \nThe velocity of wave propagation along the helix structure is less than velocity of light. \nThe beam and wave travel along the structure at the same speed. \nThus interaction occurs between beam and wave and the beam delivers energy to the RF wave. \nTherefore the signal gets strengthened and amplified output is delivered at the other end of tube. \nThe main features of TWT are :\n1. Frequency range - 0.5 GHz to 90 GHz\n2. Power output - 5 mW at low frequencies(less than 20 GHz) 250 kW (continuous wave) at 3 GHz 10 MW (pulsed) at 3 GHz\n3. Efficiency - about 5 to 20%\n4. Noise - about 5 dB for low power TWT 25 dB for high power TWT \nTWT is used as RF amplifier in broadband microwave receivers, repeater amplifier in broad band communication systems, communication satellites etc."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not a travelling wave?", "opta": "e = Em sin (\u03b2x - \u03c9t)", "optb": "e = Em cos (\u03b2x - \u03c9t)", "optc": "e = Em sin (\u03c9t - \u03b2x)", "optd": "e = Em sin (\u03b2x)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "In a travelling wave both x and t increase simultaneously so that a constant phase point moves in the direction of positive (or negative) x."}, {"question": "Both Impatt and Trapatt devices use avalanche effect", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "An Impatt diode has n+ - p - i - p + structure and is used with reverse bias. \nIt exhibits negative resistance and operates on the principle of avalanche breakdown. \nImpatt diode circuits are classified as broadly tunable circuit, low Q circuit and high Q circuit. \nThe impedance of Impatt diode is a few ohms. The word Impatt stands for Impact Avalanche Transit Time diode. \nThe features of Impatt diode oscillator are : frequency 1 to 300 GHz, Power output (0.5 W to 5 W for single diode circuit and upto 40 W for combination of several diodes), efficiency about 20%. \nIts applications include police radar systems, low power microwave transmitter etc.\nAvalanche diode can also be operated in large signal high efficiency mode called Trapped Avalanche Transit Time mode. \nThe Trapatt oscillations depend on the delay in the current caused by avalanche process. \nThe avalanche delay makes it possible to increase the diode voltage well above the breakdown voltage. \nTherefore a very rapid multiplication of charge carriers occurs. A Trapatt diode is also a negative resistance device. \nThe features of Trapatt diode oscillator are : Frequency 3 to 50 GHz, Power output 1-3 W, efficiency about 25%. \nIts applications are low power doppler radar, microwave beacon landing system etc."}, {"question": "In a directional coupler", "opta": "isolation (dB) equals coupling plus directivity", "optb": "coupling (dB) equals isolation plus directivity", "optc": "directivity (dB) equals isolation plus coupling", "optd": "isolation (dB) equals (coupling) (directivity)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Isolation equals coupling plus directivity."}, {"question": "As the frequency is increased, the charging MVAR in a cable", "opta": "decreases", "optb": "increases", "optc": "remain the same", "optd": "decreases or remains the scheme", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Charging current and MVAR are proportional to frequency."}, {"question": "Loss angle of a good quality cable is about", "opta": "1\u00b0", "optb": "30\u00b0", "optc": "70\u00b0", "optd": "90\u00b0", "ans": "A", "explanation": "For ideal dielectric loss angle is zero. For good quality cables, loss angle is very small, about 1\u00b0 only."}, {"question": "In a three cavity klystron amplifier, the oscillations are excited in", "opta": "input cavity", "optb": "output cavity", "optc": "intermediate cavity", "optd": "both (a) and (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "A Klystron is a vacuum tube used for generation/amplification of microwaves. \nAn electron beam is produced by oxide coated indirectly heated cathode and is focussed and accelerated by focussing electrode. \nThis beam is transmitted through a glass tube. The input cavity where the beam enters the glass tube is called buncher. \nAs electrons move ahead they see an accelerating field for half cycle and retarding field for the other half cycle. \nTherefore, some electrons are accelerated and some are retarded. This process is called velocity modulation. \nThe velocity modulation causes bunching of electrons. This bunching effect converts velocity modulation into density modulation of beam. \nThe input is fed at buncher cavity and output is taken at catcher cavity. \nIn a two cavity klystron only buncher and catcher cavity are used. In multi cavity klystron one or more intermediate cavities are also used. \nThe features of a multicavity klystron are :\n1. Frequency range - 0.25 GHz to 100 GHz\n2. Power output - 10 kW to several hundred kW\n3. Power gain - 60 dB (nominal value)\n4. Efficiency - about 40%.\nA multicavity klystron is used in UHF TV transmitters, Radar transmitter and satellite communication."}, {"question": "In the given figure reflection coefficient at load is", "opta": "0.6", "optb": "- 0.6", "optc": "0.4", "optd": "- 0.4", "ans": "B", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Which of the following lines is non-radiating?", "opta": "Open two wire", "optb": "Coaxial", "optc": "Both", "optd": "None of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since fields are confirmed within a coaxial cable it is non-radiating."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  The impedance of a matched load is equal to characteristic impedance of line.Reason (R): A matched termination absorbs all the power incident on it.", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct but R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong but R is correct", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Matched load means no reflections."}, {"question": "Skin effect is more pronounced at high frequencies.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Skin effect increases as frequency increases."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  The phenomenon of differential mobility is called transferred electron effect.Reason (R): GaAs exhibits transferred electron effect.", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct but R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong but R is correct", "ans": "B", "explanation": "A Gunn diode uses GaAs which has a negative differential mobility, i.e., a decrease in carrier velocity with increase in electric field. \nThis effects is called transferred electron effect. The impedance of a Gunn diode is tens of ohms.\nA Gunn diode oscillator has a resonant cavity, an arrangement to couple Gunn diode to cavity, biasing arrangement for Gunn diode and arrangement to couple RF power to load.\nApplications of Gunn diode oscillator include continuous wave radar, pulsed radar and microwave receivers."}, {"question": "Which of the following devices uses a helix?", "opta": "Klystron amplifier", "optb": "Klystron oscillator", "optc": "TWT", "optd": "Both (a) and (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "In a klystron the resonant structure limits the bandwidth. \nA TWT is a broadband device. Its main components are electron gun (to produce the electron beam) and a structure supporting the slow electromagnetic wave. \nThe velocity of wave propagation along the helix structure is less than velocity of light. \nThe beam and wave travel along the structure at the same speed. \nThus interaction occurs between beam and wave and the beam delivers energy to the RF wave. \nTherefore the signal gets strengthened and amplified output is delivered at the other end of tube. \nThe main features of TWT are :\n1. Frequency range - 0.5 GHz to 90 GHz\n2. Power output - 5 mW at low frequencies(less than 20 GHz) 250 kW (continuous wave) at 3 GHz 10 MW (pulsed) at 3 GHz\n3. Efficiency - about 5 to 20%\n4. Noise - about 5 dB for low power TWT 25 dB for high power TWT \nTWT is used as RF amplifier in broadband microwave receivers, repeater amplifier in broad band communication systems, communication satellites etc."}, {"question": "Which of the following parameters is negligible in transmission lines?", "opta": "R", "optb": "L", "optc": "C", "optd": "G", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Shunt conductance can be neglected in most of calculations."}, {"question": "The width of a radio beam from a 1 m diameter parabolic antenna at 10 GHz is about", "opta": "100\u00b0", "optb": "50\u00b0", "optc": "5\u00b0", "optd": "1\u00b0", "ans": "C", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "The diagram to show distance time history of electrons in klystron amplifier is called", "opta": "apple gate diagram", "optb": "asynchronous diagram", "optc": "bunching diagram", "optd": "velocity modulation diagram", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Applegate diagram is distance time plot."}, {"question": "Impedance level of Impatt diodes is generally lower than that of Gunn diodes", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "An Impatt diode has n+ - p - i - p + structure and is used with reverse bias. \nIt exhibits negative resistance and operates on the principle of avalanche breakdown. \nImpatt diode circuits are classified as broadly tunable circuit, low Q circuit and high Q circuit. \nThe impedance of Impatt diode is a few ohms. The word Impatt stands for Impact Avalanche Transit Time diode. \nThe features of Impatt diode oscillator are : frequency 1 to 300 GHz, Power output (0.5 W to 5 W for single diode circuit and upto 40 W for combination of several diodes), efficiency about 20%. \nIts applications include police radar systems, low power microwave transmitter etc."}, {"question": "A quarter wave line open circuited at far end behaves as", "opta": "inductance", "optb": "L and C in parallel", "optc": "capacitance", "optd": "L and C in series", "ans": "D", "explanation": "A quarter wave line o.c. at far end behaves as a series tuned circuit."}, {"question": "A line has Z0 = 300 \u2220 0\u00b0 \u03a9. If ZL = 150 \u2220 0\u00b0 \u03a9, reflection coefficient is", "opta": "0.5", "optb": "0.3333", "optc": "-0.3333", "optd": "-0.5", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Reflection coefficient"}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  A backward wave oscillator has an internal positive feedback.Reason (R): A positive feedback is necessary for sustained oscillations.", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct but R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong but R is correct", "ans": "B", "explanation": "It is somewhat similar to TWT and can deliver microwave power over a wide frequency band. \nIt has an electron gun and a helix structure. However the interaction between electron beam and RF wave is different than in TWT. \nThe growing RF wave travels in opposite direction to the electron beam. \nThe frequency of wave can be changed by changing the voltage which controls the beam velocity. \nMoreover the amplitude of oscillations can be decreased continuously to zero by changing the beam current. \nIt features are:\n1. Frequency range - 1 GHz to 1000 GHz.\n2. Power output - 10 mV to 150 mW (continuous wave) 250kW (pulsed).\nIt is used as signal source in transmitters and instruments."}, {"question": "In a microstrip transmission the signal can be easily redirected by changing the centre strip.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "A Microstrip line has a single dielectric substratc with ground plane on one side and a strip on the other face. \nIts special feature is easy access to top surface so that minor adjustments can be made after circuit fabrication. \nThe high dielectric constant of the substrate reduces guide wavelength and circuit dimensions. \nA microstrip line is the most commomly used transmission structure for microwave integrated circuits."}, {"question": "The frequency of oscillation in a backward wave oscillator can be changed by", "opta": "varying the voltage which controls beam velocity", "optb": "varying the beam current", "optc": "both by varying the beam current and by light varying the voltage which controls beam velocity", "optd": "changing the rate of thermionic emission", "ans": "A", "explanation": "It is somewhat similar to TWT and can deliver microwave power over a wide frequency band. \nIt has an electron gun and a helix structure. However the interaction between electron beam and RF wave is different than in TWT. \nThe growing RF wave travels in opposite direction to the electron beam. \nThe frequency of wave can be changed by changing the voltage which controls the beam velocity. \nMoreover the amplitude of oscillations can be decreased continuously to zero by changing the beam current. \nIt features are:\n1. Frequency range - 1 GHz to 1000 GHz.\n2. Power output - 10 mV to 150 mW (continuous wave) 250kW (pulsed).\nIt is used as signal source in transmitters and instruments."}, {"question": "A line has a phase constant of 29.8 rad/m. At 1000 MHz the wavelength is", "opta": "29.8 m", "optb": "2.98 m", "optc": "2.1 m", "optd": "0.21 m", "ans": "D", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "In the given figure the time taken by the wave to make one round trip is", "opta": "10 ns", "optb": "20 ns", "optc": "30 ns", "optd": "40 ns", "ans": "D", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "For a 50 \u03a9 resistor for 3 GHz application, the stray capacitance should be less than", "opta": "1 \u03bcF", "optb": "1 nF", "optc": "1 pF", "optd": "0.1 pF", "ans": "D", "explanation": "XC should be at least ten times greater than R. Therefore for 50 \u03a9 resistor at 3 GHz, C should be less than 0.1 pF."}, {"question": "In a travelling wave tube distributed interaction between an electron beam and a travelling wave takes place", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "In a klystron the resonant structure limits the bandwidth. \nA TWT is a broadband device. Its main components are electron gun (to produce the electron beam) and a structure supporting the slow electromagnetic wave. \nThe velocity of wave propagation along the helix structure is less than velocity of light. \nThe beam and wave travel along the structure at the same speed. \nThus interaction occurs between beam and wave and the beam delivers energy to the RF wave. \nTherefore the signal gets strengthened and amplified output is delivered at the other end of tube. \nThe main features of TWT are :\n1. Frequency range - 0.5 GHz to 90 GHz\n2. Power output - 5 mW at low frequencies(less than 20 GHz) 250 kW (continuous wave) at 3 GHz 10 MW (pulsed) at 3 GHz\n3. Efficiency - about 5 to 20%\n4. Noise - about 5 dB for low power TWT 25 dB for high power TWT \nTWT is used as RF amplifier in broadband microwave receivers, repeater amplifier in broad band communication systems, communication satellites etc."}, {"question": "The fabrication of microstrip line is done by", "opta": "photo etching", "optb": "printed circuit technique", "optc": "oxidation", "optd": "cladding", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Printed circuit techniques is used for micro strip line."}, {"question": "The condition of minimum distortion in a transmission line is", "opta": "RL = 1", "optb": "R = 0", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The condition for minimum distortion is found by equating The result is ."}, {"question": "The action of backward wave oscillator is similar to that of", "opta": "klystron amplifier", "optb": "reflex klystron oscillator", "optc": "TWT", "optd": "magnetron", "ans": "C", "explanation": "It is somewhat similar to TWT and can deliver microwave power over a wide frequency band. \nIt has an electron gun and a helix structure. However the interaction between electron beam and RF wave is different than in TWT. \nThe growing RF wave travels in opposite direction to the electron beam. \nThe frequency of wave can be changed by changing the voltage which controls the beam velocity. \nMoreover the amplitude of oscillations can be decreased continuously to zero by changing the beam current. \nIt features are:\n1. Frequency range - 1 GHz to 1000 GHz.\n2. Power output - 10 mV to 150 mW (continuous wave) 250kW (pulsed).\nIt is used as signal source in transmitters and instruments."}, {"question": "In the given figure the reflection coefficient at source end is", "opta": "1", "optb": "-1", "optc": "1/3", "optd": "-1/3", "ans": "C", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  Artificial transmission lines are frequently used in laboratories.Reason (R): An artificial transmission line can be used to represent an actual line and can also be used as a delay circuit, as attenuator, as filter network etc.", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct but R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong but R is correct", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Artificial transmission lines have many applications. One of the applications is to simulate an actual line in the laboratory."}, {"question": "In a backward wave oscillator the wave travelling along the line winds itself back and forth", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "It is somewhat similar to TWT and can deliver microwave power over a wide frequency band. \nIt has an electron gun and a helix structure. However the interaction between electron beam and RF wave is different than in TWT. \nThe growing RF wave travels in opposite direction to the electron beam. \nThe frequency of wave can be changed by changing the voltage which controls the beam velocity. \nMoreover the amplitude of oscillations can be decreased continuously to zero by changing the beam current. \nIt features are:\n1. Frequency range - 1 GHz to 1000 GHz.\n2. Power output - 10 mV to 150 mW (continuous wave) 250kW (pulsed).\nIt is used as signal source in transmitters and instruments."}, {"question": "A line is excited by a 100 V dc source. If reflection coefficients at both ends are 1 each then", "opta": "there will be no oscillations on line", "optb": "there will be only 1 or 2 oscillations on line", "optc": "there will be a finite number of oscillations on line", "optd": "the oscillations will continue indefinitely", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Because rv = 1 at each end, the line voltage will not reach a steady value and oscillations will continue indefinitely."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  A coaxial line is a non-radiating line.Reason (R): In a coaxial line the electric and magnetic fields are confined to the region between the concentric conductors.", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct but R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong but R is correct", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since the fields are confined, there is no radiation."}, {"question": "Reflex klystron oscillator is essentially a low power device", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "It uses a single cavity resonator for generating microwave oscillations. \nIts parts are electron gun, resonator, repeller and output coupling.\nIt operates on the principle of positive feed back. \nThe repeller electrode is at negative potential and sends the partially bunched electron beam back to resonator cavity. \nThis positive feedback supports oscillations. Its feature are: \n1. Frequency range - 2 to 100 GHz\n2. Power output - 10 MW to about 2 W\n3. Efficiency - 10 - 20 %\nIts applications include radar receivers, local oscillator in microwave devices, oscillator for microwave measurements in laboratories etc."}, {"question": "A 10 km long line has a characteristic impedance of 400 ohms. If line length is 100 km, the characteristic impedance is", "opta": "4000 \u03a9", "optb": "400 \u03a9", "optc": "40 \u03a9", "optd": "4 \u03a9", "ans": "B", "explanation": "and is independent of line length."}, {"question": "A matched generator (Zg = Z0) with 1 \u03a9 available. If all ports are matched, the power delivered at ports 1, 2, 3 respectively are", "opta": "0.5 W, 0.5 W, 0 W", "optb": "0 W, 0 W, 1 W", "optc": "0.33 W each", "optd": "0 W, 0.25 W, 0.25 W", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since all ports matched, input SWR = 1. No power is reflected and Pin = P4 = 1 W. \nThis power splits between ports 1 and 2. Therefore P1 = P2 = 0.5 \u03a9, P3 = 0."}, {"question": "Which TM mode in rectangular waveguide has lowest cutoff frequency?", "opta": "TM11", "optb": "TM01", "optc": "TM10", "optd": "TM21", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Hz = 0\n\n\n\nEx = \u00b1 ZTM Hy\nEy = \u00b1 ZTM Hx\nwhere E0 is the amplitude of the wave.\nThe expressions for \u03b2, \u03bbc, fc, \u03bbg, a are the same as for TE waves.\nFor TM wave the lowest cut off frequency in rectangular wave guide is for TM11 mode. \nIf , the cutoff frequency for TM11 mode is about 12% more than that for TE20 mode."}, {"question": "A resistive microwave load with ZL = 150 \u03a9 is connected to 50 \u03a9 coaxial line. SWR is", "opta": "more than 3", "optb": "less than 3", "optc": "equal to 3", "optd": "either (a) or (c)", "ans": "C", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Which of the following devices uses a slow wave structure?", "opta": "Klystron two cavity amplifier", "optb": "Klystron multicavity amplifier", "optc": "Reflex klystron oscillator", "optd": "TWT", "ans": "D", "explanation": "In a klystron the resonant structure limits the bandwidth. \nA TWT is a broadband device. Its main components are electron gun (to produce the electron beam) and a structure supporting the slow electromagnetic wave. \nThe velocity of wave propagation along the helix structure is less than velocity of light. \nThe beam and wave travel along the structure at the same speed. \nThus interaction occurs between beam and wave and the beam delivers energy to the RF wave. \nTherefore the signal gets strengthened and amplified output is delivered at the other end of tube. \nThe main features of TWT are :\n1. Frequency range - 0.5 GHz to 90 GHz\n2. Power output - 5 mW at low frequencies(less than 20 GHz) 250 kW (continuous wave) at 3 GHz 10 MW (pulsed) at 3 GHz\n3. Efficiency - about 5 to 20%\n4. Noise - about 5 dB for low power TWT 25 dB for high power TWT \nTWT is used as RF amplifier in broadband microwave receivers, repeater amplifier in broad band communication systems, communication satellites etc."}, {"question": "In a turnstile antenna two-half wave resonant wire radiators are placed at 90\u00b0 to each other in the same plane and are excited", "opta": "in phase", "optb": "in phase opposition", "optc": "90\u00b0 out of phase with each other", "optd": "45\u00b0 out of phase with each other", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Since the two wire radiators are at 90\u00b0 to each other, they have to be excited 90\u00b0 out of phase with each other."}, {"question": "A waveguide section in a microwave circuit acts as", "opta": "LP filter", "optb": "Bandpass filter", "optc": "HP filter", "optd": "Band stop filter", "ans": "C", "explanation": "It allows high frequencies."}, {"question": "In a klystron amplifier dc electron velocity is v0 and dc electron charge density is r0 the dc beam current is", "opta": "r0v0", "optb": "r0/v0", "optc": "v0/r0", "optd": "(v0/r0)2", "ans": "A", "explanation": "= coulomb |sec|m2 = current density."}]]}